Guide to the Thomas Z. Shepard Papers
Yale University Music Library
Thomas Z. Shepard Papers
1960-2014
MSS 112
Yale University Music Library
12
(26 containers)
Thomas Z. Shepard is a 12-time Grammy Award winner, producing both Classical and Broadway projects. The collection contains a wide variety of material relating to Shepard's work at Columbia and RCA Victor from approximately 1960-1990, along with some personal materials dating from the early 2000s. The largest part of the collection comprises production materials, such as text, music, and correspondence related to specific projects, and photographs taken during recording sessions.
Shepard, Thomas Z. (Thomas Zachary), 1936-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas Z. Shepard
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Z. Shepard was born in 1936, in Orange, New Jersey. He studied music at Juilliard, Oberlin College, and Yale University. In 1960, Shepard began his tenure at Columbia Records, where he spent fourteen years working under Goddard Lieberson. He later worked as co-director of CBS Masterworks, before moving to RCA in 1974. He held an executive position as Division Vice President of RCA Red Seal until 1986, and then worked in MCA's division for Broadway and Classical music until 1989. Since 1989, Shepard has worked as an independent producer, arranger, expert legal witness, and as a lecturer on both musical theater and classical music.
Shepard is a 12-time Grammy Award winner, and has produced a wide variety of Classical and Broadway projects. He produced a number of Stephen Sondheim musicals as well as original cast recordings of 1776, La Cage aux Folles, 42nd Street, Ain't Misbehavin' and Raisin. Shepard produced hundreds of classical recordings and worked with a wide range of twentieth century composers including Leonard Bernstein, Pierre Boulez, Vladimir Horowitz, Leontyne Price, Placido Domingo, and many others.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains a wide variety of material relating to Shepard's work at Columbia and RCA Victor from approximately 1960-1990, along with some personal materials dating from the early 2000s. The largest part of the collection comprises production materials, such as text, music, and correspondence related to specific projects, and photographs taken during recording sessions. Given Shepard's dedication to musical theater, the lion's share of the project files relate to musical theater productions, though some classical projects are represented. Beyond production materials, the collection also contains personal and business correspondence and publicity materials collected by Shepard such as clippings, programs, and record magazines. The collection contains a small number of sound recordings (test pressings, CDs, and tapes).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series. Series I: Scores; Series II: Project Files, c. 1967-1995; Series III: Photographs and Slides, c. 1968-2008; Series IV: Awards, 1968-2005; Series V: Correspondence, c. 1967-2000; Series VI: Clippings, programs and publicity materials, c. 1960-1994; Series VII: Sound recordings and test pressings, 1961 - 2014; and Series VIII: Diaries, documents and miscellaneous notes, c. 1962-2002.
Musicals -- Production and direction; Shepard, Thomas Z. (Thomas Zachary), 1936-
- Scores
  - Carousel, 1987 (Box 26)
    Scope and Contents
    Vocal/piano score with extensive markings. Also includes correspondence between Shepard and Barry Reiss (MCA Records' attorney).
  - Concerto for Orchestra by Bela Bartok, 1971-1972 (Box 26)
    Full score with extensive markings. Includes notes from recording sessions with Pierre Boulez and the New York Philharmonic (produced by Shepard).
- Project files, c. 1967-1995
  The Projects files series contains a variety of materials relevant to Shepard's recording projects, including correspondence, sheet music, project-related business documents, and publicity materials. The files are organized alphabetically by project title.
  - Annie Warbucks (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Battered Upright (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Also includes music for "The Invincible Upright" and "The Ancient Upright."
  - Blaming it on You (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boston Pops (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Carousel (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Columbia Records (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Crazy for You (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Encounterpoint (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Follies (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains one folder labeled "Guys and Dolls and Follies Relevant info."
  - Follies (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gypsy (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Harold Arlen Benefit (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - In the Night Kitchen (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - In the Night Kitchen (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - In the Night Kitchen (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Kismet (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Kiss of the Spiderwoman (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Last of the Just (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lincoln Portrait (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Academy of the Recording Arts and Sciences (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - New York Pops (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - No Dancing in Elevators (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Phantom Tollbooth (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Phantom Tollbooth (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Porgy and Bess (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - RCA (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gunther Schuller recording (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Secret Garden (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Secret Garden (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - A Set of Lyrical Jokes for a Friend (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Snow Queen (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Song That Got Away (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sony Projects (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sony Projects (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sony Projects (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Such Good Friends (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Such Good Friends (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Such Good Friends (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sunday in the Park with George (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Things We Do For Love (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Tribute to Mathilde (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Two by Two (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wings (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Wings (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wozzeck (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photographs and slides, 1968-2008
  - Professional and personal photos
    - "Two by Two" - Danny Kaye and Richard Rodgers (signed), 1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      signed photograph of Richard Rodgers and Danny Kaye, who were collaborators with Shepard on the production "Two by Two."
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Photographs from recording session for 1976 release of Porgy and Bess by RCA with cast of Houston Grand Opera.
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Photographs from recording session for 1976 release of Porgy and Bess by RCA with cast of Houston Grand Opera. File contains some photos from another project, likely the 1980 cast recording of 42nd Street.
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Photographs from recording session for 1976 release of Porgy and Bess by RCA with cast of Houston Grand Opera. File contains other photographs, possibly from the 1980 recording of 42nd Street.
    - Assorted personal photographs, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Various photographs of family and friends. Most photographs were printed and dated c. 1980s, but some photographs are old, undated keepsakes (perhaps from his family or early years).
    - Assorted personal photographs, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Raisin, original cast recording, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Photographs from original cast recording of Raisin (produced by Shepard, 1973).
    - Assorted production and personal photographs, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      File contains production photos from the original cast recording of Side by Side by Sondheim, as well as additional studio photographs and family photographs.
    - Assorted production photographs, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Assorted photographs from meetings with at the recording studio. File contains a group of photographs from an unidentified recording session with large orchestra and choir.
    - 42nd Street, original cast recording, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Production photos from recording session for cast recording of 42nd Street. File also includes other production photos with studio colleagues.
    - Awards ceremony with Leontyne Price, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Pictures from an awards ceremony featuring Leontyne Price (1982). File also includes some photos of recording studios during production of 42nd Street (1980)
    - 42nd Street, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Assorted production photographs, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Photographs from production and recording studios for several shows, including 42nd Street (1980).
    - Porgy and Bess, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "MCA: Shepard Head Shot", 1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Photographs from original folder labeled "MCA: Shepard Head Shot." File contains primarily negatives and copies of Shepard's head shot, as well as a few other business related photographs.
    - Oklahoma!, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Photographs documenting cast recording of Oklahoma! for RCA, 1980.
    - Assorted Photographs - Family, 1980-1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Assorted photographs, primarily family members and home/yard.
    - Assorted Photographs - Family and Metropolitan Opera/RCA Event, 1980-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Assorted photographs, primarily family members and home/yard. File also contains photos of Metropolitan Opera and RCA gala/event (exact event unknown).
    - Production Photos, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Assorted production photographs from recording studio and other events. File contains photographs of Shepard in the studio with Angela Lansbury (for recording of Sweeney Todd, 1979) and Yul Brenner (for The King and I, 1977), as well as at other work events (e.g. Grammy awards).
    - Sweeney Todd, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Production photographs from 1979 cast recording of Sweeney Todd, feat. Angela Lansbury
    - Family photographs, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Assorted color photos of family members at home.
    - Family Photographs (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Two formal photos of family members (possibly parents). Taken in front of a cruise ship and at a venue in New York State. Undated.
    - Publicity photographs and Contact Sheets, 2000-2008 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Assortment of photographs from events and performances related to Camelot and My Fair Lady. Most Camelot photographs printed from online news source.
    - Production photographs with Conductor Pierre Dervaux, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Production photographs from recording sesssion with orchestra feat. Pierre Dervaux, Richard Tucker, and Nicholas Flagello.
    - Assorted Event Photographs and Head Shots, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Files include several prints of Shepard's head shots, photographs from business events, and a couple of misc. production photographs (one incl. Rudolph Serkin).
    - Follies, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Publicity event for Follies (feat. Stephen Sondheim and Elaine Stritch). File also contains a few additional production photographs from unidentified show.
    - Family Photographs, 1969, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
      3 photographs, 2 of a woman (undated, unidentified) and one of Shepard's daughter (dated Nov. 8 1969).
    - Production Photographs, c. 1970s (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Production photographs from recording sessions. Includes photographs from recording of Two by Two (1970), orchestral work with Pierre Dervaux and Richard Tucker, and others.
    - Production Photographs, c. 1970s (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Production photos (and select head shots) related to recordings with various artists incl. Ernst Haefliger (Tenor), Pierre Dervaux, Jennie Tourel, Viktor Fuchs, Benjamin Kohon, Herbert Borodkin, and others.
    - Sunday in the Park with George, cast recording, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Photographs of recording session for original cast album feat. Bernadette Peters, Mandy Patinkin, Stephen Sondheim, and others.
    - Musical Production Photographs, c. 1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Photographs from recording session with Stephen Sondheim (unidentified musical).
    - "Professional Pix", c. 1980 - 1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      From folder, originally labeled with the following information: "Barnes and Noble Follies, SS @ Follies, RCA Opera Party, Naras @ La Guardia High, La Mancha, Skywalker Newspaper Story, 8X10s."
    - Personal Photographs and Photograph with Jimmy Carter, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Contains an assortment of family and personal photos, several of which are labeled "Lisbon '78." Includes large color photograph of quartet playing for President Jimmy Carter. Photo signed by performers.
    - Leontyne Price, Marilyn Horne in Concert at the Met, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Production photographs and photographs from press event for recording entitled "Leontyne Price, Marilyn Horne in Concert at the Met" with James Levine, as well.
    - Pacific Overtures, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Production photographs from recording session of Stephen Sondheim's Pacific Overtures.
    - Business Photographs and negatives, 1980-1986 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Three color photos. One labeled "Ivor Schlossberg, Previn, Ian McClay, TZS, All Saints Church" from July 1986. One of Shepard alone, no date. And a third with caption "The Magic Flute, Vienna, Sept. 1-4, 1980." File contains unmarked negatives (possibly unrelated to the printed photographs).
    - Side by Side by Sondheim, Original London Cast Recording, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Photographs of recording session of Side by Side by Sondheim, featuring Original London Cast (1976).
    - Company, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Photos from recording of Stephen Sondheim's Company, 1970. File also includes photographs featuring others (e.g. Leonard Bernstein), but most appear to be related to the Company recording.
    - Assorted Production Photographs, 1968-1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Photographs from a variety of recording productions and events. Files feature pictures of Stephen Sondheim, Leontyne Price, Hal Prince, Danny Kaye, Barbra Streisand, Julie Andrews (1995) and several others (at work events, etc.)
  - Photo albums, Albums have been disassembled for preservation purposes.
    - Photo Album 1, c. 1976 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Assorted production photographs. Some photos feature corporate events, and other feature recording projects. Subjects include Leonard Bernstein, Yul Brenner, Leontyne Price, and many others.
    - Photo Album 2, 1968-1976 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Assorted production photographs. Some photos feature corporate events, and other feature recording projects. Subjects include Leonard Bernstein, Yul Brenner, Leontyne Price, and many others. Some photographs taken at a New York Chapter of National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences awards ceremony.
    - Photo Album 2, continued, 1974-1986 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Assorted photographs from recording sessions and corporate events. Subjects include Stephen Sondheim, La Cage aux Folles recording session, Budapest String Quartet, among others. One group of photos labeled "King Island Christmas Listening Party 1999."
    - Photo Album 2, continued, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Personal photos of garden and home. One photo dated April 1939 of a small boy (likely Shepard).
    - Photo Album 3, c. 1976 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Assorted recording sessions. Subjects include symphonic work with Pierre Dervaux conducting, Danny Kaye (Two by Two cast recording), and others.
    - Photo Album 3, continued, c. 1984 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Cast Recording of Sunday in the Park with George (Stephen Sondheim) feat. Bernadette Peters and Mandy Patinkin.
  - Slides
    - Carousel Recording, 1987 (Box 14)
      Slides for Carousel Recording c. 1987. Steve J. Sherman "Originals."
- Awards, 1968-2005
  Plaques and paper certificates commemorating a variety of recording-industry nominations and awards. Organized chronologically.
  - Best Score from an Original Cast Show Album, George M!, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Plaque commemorating nomination for award from The National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences.
  - Best Score from an Original Cast Show Album, Dames at Sea, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Album of the Year, Classical, Berio: Sinfonia with the New York Philharmonic and Swingle Singers, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Album of the Year, Classical, Boulez Conducts Debussy, Vol. 2, Cleveland Orchestra, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Best Spoken Word Recording, Robert F. Kennedy: A Memorial, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Album of the Year, Classical, Stravinsky: Le Sacre du Printemps, Cleveland Orchestra, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Best Score from an Original Cast Show Album, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Best Score from an Original Cast Show Album, Two by Two, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Best Score from an Original Cast Show Album, Raisin, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Best Classical Orchestral Performance, Brahms: Symphony No. 1 in C Minor, Chicago Symphony Orchestra, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Best Cast Show Album, Rex, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Best Classical Orchestral Performance, Mahler: Symphony No. 3 in D Minor, Chicago Symphony Orchestra, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Best Cast Show Album, The King and I, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Best Cast Show Album, Ain't Misbehavin', 1978 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Stereo Review's Record of the Year Award, Honorable Mention for Beethoven: Sonata. Schumann: Fantasiestücke (Arthur Rubinstein), 1978 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Stereo Review's Record of the Year Award for Sweeney Todd (Original Broadway Cast), 1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Stereo Review's Record of the Year Award, Honorable Mention for Grieg: Piano Concerto in A Minor (Percy Grainger), 1979 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Stereo Review's Record of the Year Award for Rossini: L'Italiana in Algeri (Horne; Scimone cond.), 1981 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Stereo Review's Record of the Year Award for 42nd Street (Original Broadway Cast), 1981 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Grammy Nomination, Classical Producer of the Year, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Paper certificates, nominations, and award-related memorabilia, 1969-2005 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Includes several paper certificates and award nominations from various organizations (Grammy nominations, National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences, Van Cliburn Foundation, National Television Academy, and others). File also includes a brochure from the Twelfth Annual Grammy Awards (1970) and a "Grammy Awards Book" from 1974.
- Correspondence, c. 1967-2000
  Files contain business correspondence (on CBS or RCA letterhead) as well as personal correspondence, including greeting cards and friendly letters. Some letters contain information relevant to recording projects, and may correspond to files in the Projects Series.
  Arrangement
  Topical categories are indicated on the front of each folder.
  - 1967-2000 (Box 18)
    Files contain both personal correspondence (greeting cards, etc.) and business correspondence. Correspondents include Stephen Sondheim, associates from EMI Classics, and many other close friends and colleagues from across the recording industry.
  - 1990-1993 (Box 19)
    Files contain both personal correspondence (greeting cards, etc.) and business correspondence. Correspondence relevant to Man of La Mancha, Sony collaborations, and other projects.
- Clippings, programs, and publicity materials, c. 1960-1994
  Files contain a large assortment of materials including individual newspaper clippings relating to productions by Shepard, whole issues of trade magazines (e.g. Billboard, Cash Box), programs from live performances, occasional poster or publicity materials for productions Shepard was involved with, and much more.
  Material is divided by folder according to material type (e.g. magazines, programs).
  - 1960-1994 (Box 20)
    Materials include newspaper clippings, annotated articles, concert and show programs, and magazines. Subjects include Broadway shows and recordings, classical recordings and concerts, feature articles on Tom Shepard and RCA, and articles on the recording market.
  - 1965-1988 (Box 21)
    Primarily copies of industry magazines and publications, including issues of Billboard, Record World, The New York Times, Cash Box, and others. Files contain some single-page clippings and concert programs, as well.
  - 1984-1992 (Box 22)
    Files contain clippings, publicity materials, and magazines relating to several shows produced by Shepard. Shows mentioned include Porgy and Bess, Love in Two Countries, a commemorative program at the O'Neill Theater (1989), and others. Clippings from publications such as The New Yorker, Cash Box, and People Magazine. Files also include some personal notes and letters relating to clippings.
- Sound recordings and test pressings, 1961-2014 (Box 23)
  Series contains fourteen sound recordings in various formats, for the following shows/artists: Gypsy Live; Gilbert and Sullivan's Thespis; Robert Ronan; Stokowski conducting the Philadelphia Orchestra (Beethoven Symphony No. 3); Harold Arlen and Barbra Streisand; Lena Horne; Blue Paris; Spanish Fly; assorted songs; Blaming it on You (auditions).
- Diaries, documents and miscellaneous notes, 1962-2002
  Assorted correspondence, writings, sketches, business documents, and personal documents that do not immediately correspond to recording projects in Projects Series. Organized by subject (indicated in title of file).
  - Oberlin, 1991-1993 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Pamphlets, alumni magazines, and documentation relating to Shepard's alma mater, Oberlin Conservatory of Music. Some materials relate to reunions and alumni activities.
  - Greg Varner, "The Romance of the Phonograph Days" (drafts), 1989 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Typescript draft and letter.
  - Mock-up Advertisements, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    Mock-up advertisements/proof sheets for albums on MCA Records/MCA Classics.
  - Columbia/Epic Records Membership Directory, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Financial Documents (contracts, expenses, riders), 1962-1992 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Shepard (clipping and camp progress report), 1984; 1996 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Notes, Writings, and Programs, 1965-2000 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    Miscellaneous notes and drafts of musical numbers (shows unknown) and written material (likely speeches). Also contains printouts of CD reviews and other misc. material.
  - Misc. Recording Materials, 1965-1992 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    Contains materials relating to recording projects such as lists of album releases (business materails), photo credits relating to record releases, blank Columbia Records Session Data Sheets, and other materials.
  - Diaries, 1963-1988 (Box 25)
    Diaries annotated with scheduling and agendas.